Hello guys!
Welcome back to our IELTS
writing course.
After learning about marking
criteria today we're going to
move on to academic writing
style which is used for IELTS.
Our lesson today covers three main
parts which are tentative language,
objective language and formal
writing style.
The first thing we need to do is
talk about tentative language.
Firstly,
let's talk about overgeneralization.
It is when you make something
become accurate and absolute in
all circumstances.
Let's take a look at this example.
Smoking causes cancer.
However, not all smokers have cancer
because in fact there are many other
causes. Cancer. Not just smoking.
Thus you over generalize the problem.
So how can you correct this mistake?
Let's move on to the correction
and I will show you four ways.
Firstly, you can use some
frequency adverbs. For example.
Sometimes usually for example you can
write smoking often causes cancer.
The second way is that you can
use some words or phrases to
show possibilities.
May could to be likely to.
These phrases can reduce the
absolute level of the sentence.
For example, you can write smoking
may cause cancer or smoking is
likely to cause cancer.
Now let's talk about exaggeration.
It is when you indicate that
something is, for example, worse or
more important than it really is.
Here I have two examples.
The first example is.
Planting trees is a perfect way
to solve environmental problems.
The second one is using mobile
phones exerts detrimental impact
on human health.
As you can see the word perfect
in example one and detrimental
in example two.
These are absolute words saying
that something is 100% true.
So I will correct those mistakes by
using some following alternatives.
Here you can see that I replace
perfect and detrimental with
effective and adverse respectively.
By using neutral words, you can
avoid exaggeration in your writing,
so please remember to use them
instead of the exaggerated words.
After learning about tentative
language, we will move to the
second part of today's lesson,
which is objective language.
First,
let's talk about emotional words.
They are words that indicate
personal feelings and or emotions.
For example, we have some words
like really so amazing, fantastic,
horrible, disgusting especially and
special. Here are two examples.
Deforestation is a horrible
problem for us.
Planting trees is a wonderful way
to solve environmental problems.
As you can see, horrible and
wonderful are emotional words,
so you must avoid using them.
Now I will give you some other words
or phrases to replace these two.
Let's have a look at the two
following sentences.
Deforestation is an enormous and
severe a serious problem for the
human race.
Planting trees is an effective way
to solve environmental problems.
The words enormous, severe, serious,
or effective all deliver the
objectivity for two sentences above.
Therefore, you can use those
words in your writings to avoid
using emotional words.
Next,
we will move on to personal pronouns.
And for this word,
I assure you that you can
completely use it in IELTS writing.
However, please remember that I
is only used when you state your
opinion, not when you explain a
point or an idea. All right.
That's all about objective language.
We will move on to part three
formal writing style.
Firstly, we're going to talk about
informal language in formal language
or words that are too simple.
For example big go do,
make thing stuff,
etc. you may use these words in daily
conversations or in basic writings.
However, in the IELTS academic
writing, you should replace these
simple words with other alternatives.
You can still use them as parts of a
collocation, but not individually.
The second thing about informal
language is that you must avoid using
idioms, proverbs, or sayings of
famous people or something like that.
You can use them in IELTS
speaking tests,
but not in IELTS writing tests.
In the next part of formal writing
style, we're going to discuss
contractions and abbreviations
in IELTS writing or academic
writing style in general.
You are not allowed to use
contractions or abbreviations
for example. I'm there. Can't.
Don't. Doesn't. Mustn't or.
WTO, W.H.O. or IMF.
Remember that these words must
not be used in IELTS writing.
Instead, write the words out.
All right.
Let's take a look at this example.
I'm an advocate of the idea that
the role of women in modern
society can't be ignored.
Here you can see some
contractions such as I'm or cant.
They are not allowed in IELTS
writing.
Instead you have to write the
words out like this.
I am an advocate of the idea
that the role of women in modern
society cannot be ignored.
In conclusion,
do not use contractions or
abbreviations in the IELTS writing.
Instead, write the words out.
All right, we have finished the
lesson about academic writing style,
including three main parts tentative
language, objective language,
and formal writing style.
I hope you now have an overall
understanding of how to write an
IELTS essay in an academic style.
This is the end of today's lesson.
Thank you guys for listening and
I hope to see you again in the
next videos. Goodbye.